Guide to the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates Collection circa 1892-2002 (bulk undated) PR 370
New-York Historical Society
Gramercy Neighborhood Associates collection
circa 1892-2002 (bulk undated)
New-York Historical Society
Gramercy Neighborhood Associates
PR 370
.63 Linear Feet in two document boxes.
The collection primarily consists of photographs of Gramercy Park and the surrounding area, including street, park, building exteriors, and aerial views. There are also eight fiction and non-fiction books about Gramercy Park and related historical figures.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two document boxes. Box 1, a half document box, contains nine folders of photographs, relocated from an original three binders, and Box 2 contains books.
Most of the photographs are reproductions of originals and the bulk are undated. The date ranges shown in the container list are approximations of the date of the original image, not necessarily the date of the collection's copy.
Biographical / Historical
Gramercy Neighborhood Associates is a nonprofit organization made up primarily of Gramercy Park residents. The organization was founded in 1912, in part united by a collective effort to prevent the passage of a bill that would have bisected Gramercy Park in order to connect Lexington Avenue and Irving Place. Since then, Gramercy Neighborhood Associates has engaged in a variety of community service projects, including hosting events for residents such as the Annual Art Show, sponsoring neighborhood renovations such as replacing modern lampposts with Bishop Crook Lampposts in order to reestablish Gramercy's historic aesthetic, and engaging with schools and local businesses in the Gramercy Park area.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, September 2017.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of approximately 150 photographs and eight fiction and non-fiction books about Gramercy Park and related historical figures.
The photographs are of Gramercy Park and its surrounding areas, including Union Square Park, Madison Square Park, Stuyvesant Town, and Peter Cooper Village. Most of the photographs are reproductions of images from the mid 1800s through the twentieth century, though there are many original documents found throughout. The earliest original photograph appears to date from about 1892. The photographs are mainly views of streets, parks and building exteriors, along with a number of aerial shots. Images of buildings include a few under construction, such as the Flatiron Building (1902) and the Metropolitan Life Insurance building (1907-08). All of the photos are black-and-white, except for a set from 1989 taken by Consolidated Edison. The container list provides further detail, and Folder 1 contains a detailed inventory provided by the donor of the photographs' subjects.
The books in the collection are listed individually in the container list.
All materials in the collection appear to have been compiled by the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, but do not pertain to the organization itself.
Gramercy Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Aerial photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Hardcover books; Paperbacks
- Photographs (folder 1 of 9), circa 1896-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Folder includes, among other images, the parade for the cornerstone ceremony of Washington Irving School, construction of Flatiron and Metropolitan Life Insurance buildings, Episcopal Church Mission House, Fourth Ave street scene (1926), Stuyvesant Fish House/Sonnenberg Mansion, Clarendon Hotel.
- Photographs (folder 2 of 9), circa 1880s-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes, among other images, Irving Place, New Amsterdam Hotel, trolley cars and horsecars, Union Square, aerial of Madison Square Park/Metropolitan Life building area, aerial of construction site of Stuyvesant Town and Peter Cooper Village (1946), and bar at Scheffel Hall.
- Photographs (folder 3 of 9), circa 1870-1960s? (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes, among other images, interior of Scheffel Hall, Fourth Avenue Presbyterian Church, All Souls Unitarian Church, Everett House, original Metropolitan Life building at Park and 23rd (as seen in 1950s?), Gramercy Park, and street views.
- Photographs (folder 4 of 9), circa 1853-1950s? (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Includes, among other images, Gramercy Park and rowhouses surrounding the park and Stanford White house (original photos by Ameniya).
- Photographs (folder 5 of 9), circa 1898-1950s? (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes, among other images, Japanese bronze lantern from Stanford White residence, Peter Cooper and Abram S. Hewitt home after 1883 stoop alteration, and Gramercy Park statuary and scenes (including winter).
- Photographs (folder 6 of 9), circa 1892-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Includes, among other images, Christmas tree in Gramercy Park, Stanford White house, Irving Place, original photo of horsecars at Union Square in winter (1892), National Academy of Design & Lyceum Theatre (1894), aerial view of Gramercy Park, and Free Academy of New York.
- Photographs (folder 7-8 of 9), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  Color photos taken by Consolidated Edison: aerial views of 3rd Avenue and 20th Street area, and ground level views of Gramercy Park area work sites, including buildings wrapped in white sheathing.
- Photographs (folder 9 of 9), circa 1900-1950s? (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes, among other images, various views of Gramercy Park and surrounding buildings, Elsie DeWolfe house, Huyler's cocoa and chocolate factory, and George Bellows residence.
- Manhattan in Maps: 1527-1995, 1997 (Box 2)
  By Robert T. Augustyn and Paul E. Cohen.
- Gotham Comes of Age: New York Through the Lens of the Byron Company, 1892-1942, 1999 (Box 2)
  Published by the Museum of the City of New York, under the direction of Peter Simmons.
- Letters of Richard Watson Gilder, 1916 (Box 2)
  Edited by his daughter, Rosamond Gilder.
- Henry Whitney Bellows, 1979 (Box 2)
  By Walter Donald Kring.
- George Bellows: Painter of America, 1965 (Box 2)
  By Charles H. Morgan.
- Touring the Flatiron: Walks in Four Historic Neighborhoods, 1998 (Box 2)
  By Joyce Mendelsohn, for New York Landmarks Conservancy.
- Gramercy Park: A Novel, 2002 (Box 2)
  By Paula Cohen.
- Murder on Gramercy Park, 2001 (Box 2)
  By Victoria Thompson.